On the 26th of April 1923, Prince Albert,
Duke of York, married Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon
at Westminster Abbey. He was the younger
son of King George V of the United Kingdom,
and she came from a largely Scottish noble
family. Albert, known to his family as Bertie,
was not supposed to become a king and Elizabeth
was never meant to be a queen. That duty was
intended to fall to Bertie’s older brother Edward.
Had he been the heir to the throne, it is likely
Albert’s parents would have pushed him to marry a
daughter of one of Europe’s royal households. But
fate would align in strange ways. Thirteen years
later Albert’s older brother briefly became king
in January 1936 and abdicated in December. Thus,
Bertie was thrust into taking up a crown he never
wanted. It was only then that the wisdom of
his marriage became clear. As King George VI,
Bertie relied greatly on his wife to overcome
his own natural shyness and reserved character.
With Elizabeth by his side, his reign was
a successful one, leading Britain through
the Second World War and the shifting position
of the monarchy in its aftermath. This is the
story of King George VI and the Queen Mother, the
unlikely king and queen of the United Kingdom.
The man known to history as King George VI of
Britain was born as Albert Frederick Arthur George
on the 14th of December 1895 at York Cottage on
the Sandringham Estate in Norfolk, England.
His father was Prince George, Duke of York, a
grandson of Queen Victoria, who at the time of
Albert’s birth was nearing the end of her sixth
decade on the throne of Britain. She was also
the first Empress of India and ruled the vast
British overseas empire, on which it was said
the sun never set. Until shortly before Albert’s
birth, Prince George had been out of the direct
line of succession to the throne. Once Victoria
died, George’s father, Albert, Prince of Wales,
would become king. But it had been assumed until
the early 1890s that George’s older brother,
Albert Victor, as Victoria’s eldest male heir,
would ascend to the throne in due course. However,
Albert Victor died prematurely in 1892, ensuring
that the future George VI’s father became second
in line to the throne from 1892 onwards. Thus,
Albert was born in 1895 into a household which
would someday most likely constitute Britain’s
immediate royal family with his father as king and
his mother as queen consort. However, Albert was
not his father’s heir. An older brother, Edward,
had been born in the summer of 1894, a year and a
half before Albert and Edward was third in line to
the throne. Consequently, from the moment he was
born in the winter of 1895, Albert was the fourth
in line to the throne of Britain, though he would
only succeed to that position should something
ever happen to displace his older brother
Edward. As we shall see, something did occur.
Albert’s mother was Mary of Teck, a member of the
German royal house of Teck which held extensive
estates in the unified German Empire. Albert
was her and George’s second child after Edward.
Four more children would follow, Mary in 1897,
Henry in 1900, George in 1902 and John in 1905,
though John suffered from severe epilepsy from
which he would die in 1919 when only 13 years
of age. Albert, who quickly became known
to his family as ‘Bertie’, the same name
given to his grandfather, was baptised at St Mary
Magdalene Church in Sandringham just a few weeks
after he was born. Thereafter he was largely
reared in a separate household to his parents,
an entirely normal practice amongst the royal
families of Europe in the nineteenth century.
This continued through his early childhood years,
during which Albert, Edward and their growing
brood of siblings were chaperoned between royal
palaces and cottages, taught by tutors in the
standard subjects of the Victorian educational
curriculum, which in those days still involved
learning Latin and had a strong focus on the
classics of ancient Greek and Roman literature.
Albert’s parents were distant figures, who some
historians and observers have since deemed to have
been neglectful. This is too harsh an assessment
and if they seemed to be cold parents it was in
line with the conventions of the time. Albert’s
father was also a strict disciplinarian. It was
perhaps on account of the traumatic elements of
his youth that he began to suffer from a stutter
in his younger years, one which would continue to
plague him into adulthood, though as we will see,
he largely triumphed over it in his
thirties, well before he became king.
When he was just 14 years old, Albert was
sent to the Royal Naval College at Osborne on
the Isle of Wight, a training school for royals
and sons of the British aristocracy to train as
officer cadets. This followed a well-established
tradition and Albert’s father had also been sent
to join the British Royal Navy when he was barely
a teenager. Albert, it must be said, was not a
great student of any kind. He came bottom of his
class in the cadets’ final exam at Osborne, while
he was physically not predisposed to seafaring,
having suffered from stomach issues as a youth.
His confidence was also low in his younger years,
in part owing to his stutter and also because of
having been forced to learn to write with his
right hand, even though he was left-handed.
Although it seems nonsensical to the modern mind,
this was a common feature of schooling in the late
nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. It was
also while he was at Osborne that his grandfather,
King Edward VII, died. With this his father
ascended the throne as King George V and
Albert’s older brother Edward became the Prince
of Wales and heir to the throne. Albert was now
second in line to the throne, though something
unexpected would need to befall Edward for him
to ever become king. Meanwhile, in the early 1910s
he continued to progress through the Royal Navy,
joining the Royal Naval College at Dartmouth
after his sojourn at Osborne and then taking
in several training tours in 1912 and 1913,
voyages which saw him traversing much of the
Atlantic in the Caribbean and off the seaboard
of North America. In late 1913 he was finally
posted to the HMS Collingwood as a midshipman.
Albert was still struggling to find his sea legs,
an occupational hazard for a mariner, as
diplomatic tensions were building in Europe
in 1914. For decades the continent’s great powers
had been engaged in ongoing rivalries for regional
power in Europe and for possession of colonies
overseas in Africa and southern Asia. Russia and
Britain, for instance, had been rivals for a time
in Central Asia where they both had interests in
countries like Afghanistan. The French and the
Italians both had interests in North Africa and
the Horn of Africa. Since the 1890s Germany,
which had emerged as a major power on the
continent following unification in 1871, began
trying to build its own overseas empire. Armed
alliances had even developed, with Britain, France
and Russia forming the Triple Entente and Germany
having a long-standing alliance with the Empire
of Austria-Hungary. Yet despite these rivalries, a
major conflict had been avoided for many years. As
a result, when diplomatic tensions began brewing
between Austria-Hungary, Russia and Serbia in
the Balkans in July 1914 many believed that this
crisis, like many before it, would pass quickly.
It did not, and in the final days of July tensions
escalated rapidly, leading to a succession of
declarations of war. By early August nearly
every country in Europe had committed to one side
or another as Britain, France and Russia went to
war with Germany, Austria-Hungary and the Ottoman
Empire. The First World War had commenced.
In the early stages of it, Albert was
fighting another kind of conflict,
one with his appendix. In late August a medical
evaluation determined that he needed to have his
operated upon and when his ship made port in the
Scottish city of Aberdeen it was removed. After
a sufficient period of rest and convalescence he
returned to service on board the HMS Collingwood.
The ship spent most of the war stationed in the
North Sea patrolling the vast waters between
Britain north to Iceland and east towards Norway.
While Britain was the pre-eminent naval power of
the day and had been so for two centuries,
the Germans had spent an enormous amount of
money building a sizeable navy in the ten or so
years leading up to the war. Accordingly there
was an expectation that major naval engagements
would occur in the North Atlantic before long,
but in the end the war at sea was very limited
by comparison with the carnage occurring in the
trenches of the Western Front in France.
Therefore Albert spent much of late 1914,
all of 1915 and into early 1916 on board the
Collingwood undertaking gunnery drills and patrols
in the waters north of Scotland, but seeing
little active engagement with the enemy.
Albert was present for the largest naval clash
between Britain and Germany during the war.
The Battle of Jutland took place over
the course of the 31st of May and the
1st of June 1916 in the waters off the coast
of western Denmark and north-western Germany
as both sides sought to score a tactical
breakthrough at sea which might turn the
course of the war. The British had the greater
number of ships, with just over 150 vessels,
28 of them being the Dreadnought battleships, the
foremost military vessel of the day, supplemented
by nearly eighty destroyer class ships. The
German armada was just under a hundred ships,
with just 16 Dreadnoughts. Over 60% of its vessels
were torpedo boats and the German attack would
rely on these scoring a number of hits before
they ran out of torpedoes in order for the
Germans to emerge out of the clash victorious. In
the ensuing naval melee Albert served as a junior
officer aboard the HMS Collingwood. He performed
well during the battle and was mentioned as such
in the dispatches, but the battle was a mixed
affair overall. As the British and German fleets
engaged with each other across a large stretch
of sea, the Germans ultimately scored more hits,
sinking 14 ships while only losing 11, while the
British also lost a disproportionately higher
number of destroyers and larger battleships and
over twice as many mariners. As such, the Germans
statistically won the Battle of Jutland, but it
was a Pyrrhic victory, one in which the Germans
lost vital naval resources. In its aftermath
Berlin decided to prioritise submarine warfare
and there would be no second major naval clash of
this kind again during the First World War.
Albert would spend much of the war away from
active service, in large part owing to renewed
ill health. Early in 1917 he began suffering from
a duodenal ulcer and he would eventually have to
have this operated on early that winter. When he
returned to duty it was as part of the burgeoning
RAF, the Royal Air Force, which was formed on
the 1st of April 1918 as the first independent
air force operated by any nation anywhere in
the world, a sign of how air warfare had become
a central component of military conflict in the
course of the war, where at its outset planes had
been used almost exclusively for reconnaissance
missions. As a result of this decision,
Albert became the first member of the British
royal family to hold a pilot’s licence, while
in October 1918 he would fly over the English
Channel after being posted to France. The newly
created RAF only had a limited role to play in
the war in the end, though. By the summer of 1918
the trajectory of the war was clear. The entry of
the United States into the conflict on the side of
Britain and France the previous year had brought
an insurmountable amount of resources to bear
against Germany, Austria-Hungary and the Ottomans.
In the end, before victory was won on the field of
battle, political unrest across Central Europe
brought about the collapse of the German and
Austro-Hungarian empires, bringing the war to an
end in November 1918.
In the aftermath of the war Bertie returned to
land and civilian life. He began studying at
Cambridge University in the autumn of 1919. He was
23 years of age commencing his time in college,
but this was not unusual in the post-war years
when many freshman students were young men heading
towards their mid-twenties who had spent their
late teens and early twenties in the trenches in
France. He began attending Trinity College there
alongside his brother, Prince Henry, who was four
years his junior. Albert chose to study history
primarily and was tutored by Reginald Laurence,
the editor of the Cambridge Modern History and
an expert on both ecclesiastical history and the
French Revolution, though the most substantial
scholar to teach Albert at this time was Dennis
Robertson, an economic historian and close
colleague of John Maynard Keynes, the founder
of the Keynesian economic theory. At Cambridge
Louis Greig, who Albert had none since his days at
Osborne a decade earlier, was employed as Bertie’s
equerry or royal assistant. They developed a keen
friendship over their shared interest in tennis
and the pair would later play together at the
Championships at Wimbledon. Albert’s time at
Cambridge, though, was cut short after just three
terms as he was increasingly drawn into becoming
a working royal in the early 1920s, spending much
of his time from 1920 onwards visiting industrial
factories and mines across England as the monarchy
sought to establish closer ties to the working
classes in Britain at a time when radical
socialism was on the front foot across Europe.
Because he was the second son of the king and at
a time when premature death was beginning to
decline dramatically, it was expected in the
1910s and 1920s that Albert would never be King
of Britain. Therefore he was given something of
a free hand to choose his own marriage partner,
a relatively novel development for a monarch’s
child. Had he been born in the nineteenth century,
for instance, a marriage to a daughter of one of
Europe’s royal households would most likely
have been arranged. Nevertheless, when Albert
began an affair in 1919 with Sheila Chisholm it
aroused consternation in the royal establishment.
This Australian ‘it-girl’ of the 1910s was
already married to Francis St Clair-Erskine,
Lord Loughborough. Bertie met Sheila after his
older brother Edward began seeing Chisholm’s
best friend, Freda Dudley Ward. The relationship
dragged on for almost a year before King George,
exasperated by the situation instructed Bertie to
leave this, quote, “already married Australian”.
Albert was not happy with doing so, but obeyed his
father’s command. His brother’s unwillingness to
abide by a similar injunction from the king over
a decade later would have striking consequences
for both Edward and Albert in the long run.
In the shorter term Albert was compensated for
ending his affair with Lady Loughborough by being
invested with the title of Duke of York in 1920,
one of the most historically significant peerages
in British history and one which had been vacant
since his father abandoned the title upon becoming
king in 1910.
Bertie’s attentions were soon drawn elsewhere in
his quest for a marriage partner. Shortly after
ending his relationship with Lady Loughborough,
he met Lady Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon at an engagement.
They had known each other as children, but had
not crossed paths in several years. By the time
they met again Elizabeth was just entering her
twenties and Albert, by then in his mid-twenties,
was evidently smitten. He proposed in
1921, but Elizabeth turned down his offer,
fearful that entering the royal family and the
public gaze that came with it would result in
her being stifled and unable to express her
true self in years to come. Bertie, though,
would not take no for an answer and was determined
to woo her. A second marriage proposal came
following Albert’s sister Mary’s wedding to the
heir to the Viscount Lascelles in February 1922,
at which Elizabeth had acted as a bridesmaid. She
again said no, but further months of courtship
evidently swayed her and in January 1923,
despite her reservations about entering the royal
establishment, she said yes to Albert on his third
time of asking. The wedding was swiftly organised
and the couple were married at Westminster Abbey
in London on the 26th of April 1923. Thereafter
they proceeded on their honeymoon, at the start
of which Elizabeth contracted whooping cough
in what she later called a thoroughly unromantic
development. Despite this inauspicious beginning,
the marriage was to be a notably happy one by
the standards of many royal unions and Albert
and Elizabeth had a genuine affection for
one another. It was in many ways the first
modern royal marriage in British history.
While the honeymoon might have been interrupted
by a bout of whooping cough, there was inevitably
a longer diplomatic tour to be undertaken by the
couple following their marriage. It was typical
for newlywed senior royals at this time to tour
the British Empire so that in an age before
television the people of India, Canada and
many other parts of Britain’s dominions could have
an opportunity to see the new member of the royal
family. This commenced with a visit to Northern
Ireland in July 1924, no doubt in an effort to
reassure the Unionist community there of crown
support for their continued presence within the
United Kingdom following the establishment of the
Irish Free State on the rest of the island during
the early 1920s. A tour of Britain’s colonies
in Africa followed, taking in Kenya, Uganda and
Sudan, as well as Aden in the south of the Arabian
Peninsula, though the Duke and Duchess of York
avoided Egypt where the British Governor-General,
Sir Lee Stack, had just been assassinated on the
streets of Cairo in November 1924. They returned
to England for a time thereafter in order for
Elizabeth to give birth to their first child in
1926, a daughter named Elizabeth after her mother.
She was the first of their two children, with
another girl named Margaret following in 1930.
As soon as Elizabeth was born in 1926 and her
mother had recovered, the Duke and Duchess resumed
their tour of Britain’s overseas colonies. In 1927
they headed west across the Atlantic. They first
visited Jamaica, where Albert notably played a
doubles tennis match alongside Bertrand Clark,
an all-round sporting figure who had competed
internationally in golf, tennis and cricket.
In 1924 Clark had become the first black athlete
to compete at the Wimbledon tennis Championships
in London, a tournament which Albert had himself
competed at in 1926, partnering his friend and
mentor Louis Greig, the Scottish naval surgeon
who had served as his equerry at Cambridge,
in the men’s doubles event. Admittedly they
were soundly beaten in the first round but
Albert remains the only British royal
to have competed at the Championships,
having done so when the Championships were
still an amateur event. Albert’s decision to
play alongside Clark in Jamaica the following year
was seen as an inclusive decision which embraced
the wider Jamaican population. It was probably
simply more in line with Albert’s personality
that he innocently decided to play a game of
tennis and wasn’t considering the political
overtones of doing so at all. Thereafter, he and
Elizabeth proceeded onwards to the Pacific Ocean,
visiting Fiji, New Zealand and Australia, before
returning to Britain after taking in many of the
empire’s countries in the mid-1920s.
While in Australia Albert oversaw the formal
opening of the newly built Parliament House in
the capital city, Canberra. He delivered a speech
during this event, one which was well delivered.
This would not have been possible just a year or
two earlier. Bertie’s stutter had not retreated
with the passage of the years and by the mid-1920s
had become a problem. When he had given the
closing speech at the British Empire Exhibition at
Wembley in October 1925, the ceremony had been an
endurance test for both Albert and his listeners,
with the Duke struggling to deliver his lines.
In its aftermath he determined to do something
to confront the stutter which had plagued him
since his youth. Thus, although the acclaimed
film The King’s Speech, depicts Albert as having
employed him much later in the lead up to and
opening stages of the Second World War, it was
actually in 1926 that Bertie first began working
with Lionel Logue, an Australian former stage
actor turned speech and language therapist.
Logue’s methods were unusual by the standards
of the 1920s and he was considered a quack by
many in the medical community, but his regimen of
daily vocal exercises and conscious relaxing of
the throat muscles proved enormously successful
in Albert’s case. Already when he had opened the
Parliament House in Canberra in 1927 the Duke’s
speech was much improved and his voice did not
falter on that occasion. He continued to
work with Logue intermittently over the
next twenty years and in 1937, at the time of his
coronation, he honoured the Australian by making
him a Member of the Royal Victorian Order, with
promotion to the rank of Commander in 1944.
More broadly, Albert grew into himself in
the 1920s. He was a changed man following
his marriage and after becoming a father
and unlike his own father and grandfather
his parenting style was a warm, modern one,
rather than being a cold, distant presence
in his daughters’ lives. The family originally
lived at White Lodge in Richmond Park in London,
but they moved to a more modest home in Piccadilly
in 1926. During these years the Duke and Duchess
became known for their philanthropy. Bertie, for
instance, founded the Industrial Welfare Society
through which he met with trade unionists and
other leaders of industrial workers to try to
gain a greater understanding of the material
existences of Britain’s workers and how their
lot could be improved at a time when industrial
communities in much of England and Scotland still
suffered from striking deprivation. Bertie
became known as ‘the Foreman’ to his family,
such was his interest in labour issues. He also
established the Duke of York’s Camps through
which boys from working class communities
and public schools competed in a wide range
of events. These were a forerunner of the Duke
of Edinburgh Awards latterly established by his
son-in-law. Albert took a great personal interest
in them and attended the camps every year in the
late 1920s and throughout the 1930s except for
1934 when he was ill.
In the late 1920s and early 1930s Albert and
Elizabeth must surely have believed that their
lives would continue on the same trajectory as
they had been on since their marriage. They would
continue to play prominent roles in representing
the royal family as Duke and Duchess of York,
but the assumption was there that Bertie’s
older brother Edward would eventually marry,
become king, produce an heir and the royal line
would continue through his family. However,
by the early 1930s it was imperative for
Edward to marry at some point, as he neared
his fortieth year. It was worrying for both the
king and the government to discover in the course
of the mid-1930s that Edward’s attentions had
actually landed on Wallis Simpson, an American
divorcee who had come to England following her
marriage in 1928 to Ernest Aldrich Simpson,
an American businessman with extensive dealings in
England. Edward and she had first met in 1932 and
gradually entered into an extra-marital affair. By
1935 when King George sanctioned the Metropolitan
Police Special Branch to begin monitoring
Simpson’s movements, the relationship between
her and the heir to the throne had become a matter
of considerable concern to the royal family and
the Conservative Party Prime Minister, Stanley
Baldwin, when he entered government that summer.
Although news of the affair had not become public
knowledge at that time, it was widely believed
that if it did it would become a cause of major
scandal, both because Simpson was a divorcee at
a time when divorce still carried considerable
social stigma and also because Edward and she
were romantically involved while Wallis was still
married to her second husband. The affair would
soon change the course of Albert’s life.
Albert’s father, King George V, died on the 20th
of January 1936, in large part owing to a lung
condition exacerbated by lifelong chain smoking,
underlying medical conditions and habits which
were shared by his sons and which plagued their
later lives as well. He had been considerably
ill since the mid-1920s, but by 1935 matters
were very poor indeed. In his final months he had
expressed his hopes that if Edward continued with
his relationship with Simpson that they would
not have children and that the way would soon
be clear for Albert to succeed to the throne one
day. That would come sooner rather than later.
Although Edward immediately ascended to the throne
as King Edward VIII following his father’s death
in January 1936, there were discussions taking
place immediately within Baldwin’s government
about what course should be followed if Edward
insisted on marrying Simpson. As Edward did
not have any children, Albert was necessarily
part of these discussions from their inception,
as he was next in line to the throne. It was clear
that if Edward were forced to abdicate, Albert
would almost certainly succeed him, although
there were rumours in the mid-to-late 1930s that
the government was considering the possibility of
one of Albert’s two younger brothers, Prince Henry
and Prince George, as possible candidates
to succeed Edward if the crisis deepened.
George, it was held at the time, was viewed in
particular as a possible king, as he and his wife,
Princess Marina of Greece and Denmark, had
become parents to a son, Prince Edward,
in October 1935 and thus he would have a male
heir already if he became king. However, there
is no evidence to suggest that the idea of Henry
or George succeeding Edward was ever seriously
entertained by Baldwin’s government and the plan
from the very start of the Abdication Crisis
was for Albert to succeed his brother if Edward
ended up renouncing his throne.
Edward’s coronation was planned for the 12th of
May 1937. He would not remain as king for long
enough for it to be held though. The first months
of his reign saw a growing standoff with Baldwin
concerning his relationship with Wallis Simpson.
Edward was seemingly determined to marry her and
for her part Wallis was taking steps to divorce
her second husband in advance of marrying Edward.
She had informed friends that she expected to be
crowned as queen the day that Edward was crowned
as king. This would not be the case. Baldwin was
utterly opposed to Edward’s proposed marriage and
in the autumn of 1936 began liaising extensively
with the wider royal family, particularly Bertie,
who was reluctantly acclimatising himself to
the reality of succeeding his brother within
a matter of weeks, a development which he had
no desire to see occurring. News of the affair
eventually broke and it was made known to the
nation in the newspapers on the 2nd of December
1936. Thereafter, despite efforts by some senior
members of parliament such as Winston Churchill to
support Edward’s right to marry whom he pleased,
it became abundantly clear that parliament sided
with Baldwin’s approach. Pressured into
making a swift decision, Edward agreed to
abdicate rather than end his relationship with
Simpson. He did so on the 11th of December,
upon which Albert succeeded as King of Britain and
Emperor of India, taking the regnal name George VI
in honour of his father. He was a reluctant king
and later revealed that when he had to visit his
mother and tell her the news of the abdication
and his assumption of the throne, he wept.
George rose to the position of king well.
His style of rule was modest and undramatic,
in stark contrast to the controversy and drama
which had surrounded Edward as Prince of Wales
and during his brief time as king. Over the
next fifteen or so years he would fulfil the
role of monarch and its constitutional remit
very well, rarely exceeding the role which
the monarchy was largely confined to by the
middle of the twentieth century, which was to
represent the royal establishment well and act
in a ceremonial capacity. Nevertheless, this was
still an important function, particularly so when
Britain entered a period of extreme hardship from
the autumn of 1939 onwards. Moreover, George’s
modest and unassuming personality was a good
foil to the larger than life character of
Winston Churchill as Prime Minister when
war would come just a few years into his reign.
Politically George was conservative in his views,
but not staunchly so and was well-suited
to overseeing the gradual modernisation of
the country both socially and culturally.
George had come to power at a time when the
political map of Europe was in flux. Following the
end of the First World War in 1918, the continent
had experienced five years of brutal revolutions
and civil wars in regions like Russia, Turkey,
Poland, Ireland and Germany. But eventually in
1923 and 1924 the chaos subsided and several
years of major economic growth and prosperity
had followed. This was checked by the Wall
Street Crash in the autumn of 1929 and the Great
Depression which followed. As renewed political
turmoil arose across Europe many countries turned
to more extreme politics. In Central Europe,
in particular, far-right nationalist and fascist
parties had emerged to claim power in countries
like Austria, Hungary and above all Germany where
the Nazis led by Adolf Hitler seized power early
in 1933. Conversely, Eastern Europe was dominated
by the totalitarian Soviet Union led by Joseph
Stalin. Those few countries which retained a
democratic governmental system were threatened
by the vying forces of fascism and communism and
shortly before George succeeded to the throne a
bitter civil war had broken out in Spain between
these left and right-wing political forces.
The task before Britain in the first years of
George’s reign was to navigate this difficult
political environment, preventing the rise of
both the British Union of Fascists under Oswald
Mosley and excessive social unrest wrought by
the political left. And George’s task in acting
as head of state at this time was not helped
by Edward and Wallis’s decision to undertake
an unofficial tour of Nazi Germany in the autumn
of 1937, one in which Edward clearly displayed his
appreciation of German National Socialism.
When George became king, Britain was at a
crossroads in terms of how to approach the German
threat. It could begin rearming rapidly in order
to deter Germany from further aggression
or try to appease Hitler and the Nazis by
granting them concessions, principally in the
shape of reversals of some of the more punitive
aspects of the Treaty of Versailles which
had brought the First World War to an end.
George was in many ways a favourer of appeasement,
but the principle architect of this approach was
Neville Chamberlain who succeeded Baldwin in
May 1937 when he stood down as Prime Minister.
Chamberlain continued a policy of slow rearmament,
while also allowing Germany to re-emerge as the
major power in Central Europe. Thus, few
objections were raised when the Anschluss,
the union of Germany and Austria into a Greater
Germany, was undertaken by the Nazis in March 1938
in direct violation of the peace treaties which
had brought the war to an end. George supported
Chamberlain in this approach, but in doing so he
was actually following the constitutional remit of
the monarchy by the 1930s, which was to support
the government of the day and its decisions,
regardless of whether or not those same policies
ran contrary to the monarch’s own views.
In one instance, and a particularly significant
one at that, George did directly associate
himself with Chamberlain’s policy. Following
the annexation of Austria in the spring of
1938 the Nazis had turned their attention to
the Sudetenland, the German-speaking region of
western Czechoslovakia, making claims to this
territory. Eventually a diplomatic conference
was convened to be held in Munich in September
1938. In the lead up to it George offered to
write directly to Hitler to try to appeal to him
as one ex-serviceman to another to try to prevent
war. This was well-intended, though considerably
naïve in retrospect. When Chamberlain reached an
agreement with Hitler at Munich to allow Germany
to annex the Sudetenland in return for a promise
of no further aggressive actions or claims on
its neighbours’ territory, George sent him a
message requesting him to visit Buckingham Palace
immediately on his return to England so that the
king could express his immense congratulations
on what he perceived to be a major diplomatic
victory. The appearance of the monarch and the
Prime Minister on the balcony of Buckingham
Palace together when Chamberlain arrived in
England was a striking statement about their
combined belief in the success of appeasement. But
they would soon realise how misguided their faith
in the agreement reached at Munich was.
In the summer of 1939, despite the troubled
political headwinds in Europe, George and
Elizabeth headed across the Atlantic Ocean
and visited the United States. The tour of the
US was undertaken on the invitation of Present
Franklin D. Roosevelt. Occurring between the 7th
and 12th of June, it has a significance as being
the first time that a British monarch had ever
visited the country. No British monarch had agreed
to do so since the US, which had been born out of
Britain’s colonies in North America, had declared
its independence in 1776 and even prior to this
no monarch had visited the colonies since their
establishment in the early seventeenth century.
The tour took in much of the East Coast, with
visits to Washington D.C. and New York as well
as Mount Vernon, the home of George Washington in
Virginia. The state visit was an important one in
making the British royals visible to the American
public and was conceived of by Roosevelt as a way
of generating support in the US for providing aid
to Britain in the event of war breaking out.
It was a shrewd diplomatic move, one which did
not see US sentiment in favour of intervening in
the Second World War when it initially broke out,
but which helped Roosevelt to persuade Congress
to provide financial and material support to
Britain in the early stages of the war.
Close ties between Britain and the US would
soon be needed, as Chamberlain’s efforts
at appeasement were proven to have been in
vain by the time George and Elizabeth toured
the US in the summer of 1939. No sooner had
the dust settled on the Munich Agreement and the
Sudetenland been annexed into a greater Germany,
than Hitler and the other senior members of
the Nazi regime began turning their attentions
towards further land grabs. The winter of 1938
was relatively calm, but the following March
the Munich accords were torn up as German troops
entered Czechoslovakia and occupied the country
which became a protectorate of Nazi Germany. Just
days later the city of Memel on the Baltic Sea
coast was annexed after being threatened with an
aerial bombardment by the German foreign minister,
Joachim von Ribbentrop. By now Britain and
France had begun to accelerate the speed of
their rearmament in preparation for the inevitable
conflict, but they were far behind where they
needed to be. The Nazis were aware of this and
consequently accelerated their own march to war.
In the summer of 1939 their attentions turned
to Poland, making diplomatic claims to Polish
territory which Germany had been forced to cede
in 1919 as part of the Treaty of Versailles which
brought the First World War to an end. Finally, in
late August 1939 a false flag operation was run to
make Poland seem like the aggressor in Eastern
Europe. On the 1st of September 1939 Germany
declared war on its eastern neighbour and invaded
Poland. Two days later, in response to this
aggression, Britain and France went to war with
the Nazis. The Second World War had commenced.
As the King of Britain and Emperor of India the
task fell to George on the 3rd of September 1939
to address the nation upon Britain’s declaration
of war on Germany earlier that day. At 6pm that
evening he delivered his speech, broadcast over
the radio. While Winston Churchill’s addresses to
the nation during the war usually garner greater
attention, George’s on Britain’s entry into the
war was also galvanising. In it he stated, “In
this grave hour, perhaps the most fateful in our
history, I send to all my peoples, both at home
and over seas, this message with the same depth
of feeling for each one of you as if I were able
to cross your threshold and speak to you myself.
For the second time in the lives of most
of us we are at war. Over and over again
we have tried to find a peaceful way out of the
differences between ourselves and those who are
now our enemies. But it has been in vain…If
one and all be resolutely faithful today,
ready for whatever service or sacrifice it may
demand, with God’s help we shall prevail.”
George’s maiden speech to the nation
during the conflict was delivered
without any trace of the stutter which
had plagued him for much of his youth.
Although the award-winning film The King’s Speech
contains many aspects of George’s story which are
historically accurate, his challenges concerning
his stutter were primarily faced and overcome
with the assistance of Lionel Logue in the
mid-to-late 1920s, though George did periodically
consult with Logue over the years including
during the Second World War. Nevertheless,
the film is inaccurate in suggesting that the king
only began to confront his stutter in the period
immediately before the war.
With the onset of the war there was a growing
problem in the heart of government. Neville
Chamberlain remained as Prime Minister and
retained the support of the bulk of the
Conservative Party. However, there was a
rebellious faction amongst the Tories and many
in Britain felt that Chamberlain’s position was
untenable given that he had championed the
policy of appeasing Germany after he became
Prime Minister in 1937. Matters came to a head
in early May 1940 during the so-called Norway
Debate in the House of Commons, which began
concerning British efforts to open a front in
Northern Norway following the country’s occupation
by the Nazis, but which soon morphed into a wider
debate on Chamberlain’s management of the war.
It became clear that he could not remain on as
Prime Minister, but there was a debate as to who
should succeed him, with some favouring Winston
Churchill, a long-standing Conservative critic of
the Nazis and appeasement and others supporting
the candidature of Lord Halifax, an ally of
Chamberlain’s who was not entirely opposed to
negotiating peace terms with Germany. George
was initially in support of Halifax, holding
a grudge against Churchill over his support for
Edward and opposition to George becoming king
back in the early winter of 1936. However, as
events unfolded in the early summer of 1940 it
became clear that Churchill was the candidate who
could command cross-party support in parliament
and on the 10th of May 1940 George asked Churchill
to form a new government. The case was urgent,
as the Germans had invaded Belgium and the
Netherlands that morning heading towards France.
A cross-party coalition government conceived
on the widest basis was soon established.
Though he opposed Churchill’s ascent as Prime
Minister initially, once he occupied 10 Downing
Street, the relationship between George and
Winston became one of the closest between any
British monarch and Prime Minister in modern
history. The exigencies of the war ensured
that they had to meet regularly and they soon
bonded over their common interest in the Navy,
Churchill having served as First Lord of the
Admiralty during the First World War while George
was at sea in the North Atlantic. Things grew from
there. By the late autumn of 1940 their formal
meetings had been replaced by informal lunches
between king and prime minister every Tuesday,
ones which would often last for several hours
and in which Churchill related the actions of
government, while George explained what he
felt the mood of the nation was based on
his extensive meetings with the public, which
were taking place on an almost daily basis.
We know of the considerable friendship which
developed between the pair in the course of the
war owing to George having recorded them regularly
in his diary. It was not always smooth sailing,
notably in the spring of 1944 when Churchill
had to convince the king that he could not
take part in the D-Day landings, not even
on board the warships at the rear once the
beachheads had been secured, but generally
the relationship was a successful one,
in large part because Churchill encouraged
George, a naturally shy and retiring man,
that he had a considerable public role to play in
the war. He made him feel useful. A sign of their
affinity for one another would be seen many years
later, when Churchill was delivered the news of
George’s passing at 10 Downing Street, he was
said to have laid aside his papers and stated,
“Bad news, the worst”, and descended into a deep
gloom for several days.
George’s close relationship with Churchill was
in many ways forged in the dark days of the
autumn of 1940. Following the Nazi invasion and
rapid conquest of the Low Countries and France
in the summer of 1940 the Blitz, a bombing
campaign of Britain initiated by the Nazis,
combined with a naval blockade of Britain in
the North Atlantic, commenced. The Blitz began
on the 7th of September with the goal of bringing
Britain to negotiate peace terms without the Nazis
having to launch a land invasion of Britain.
London was the prime target from the beginning,
but George and Elizabeth took the decision
to remain in the capital. It was a hazardous
decision. Over 1,000 people alone were killed
in the city on the first night of the bombing
campaign and on the 13th of September the king
and queen were very nearly killed when several
bombs landed on Buckingham Palace. More broadly,
the royal family underwent the same rationing that
was imposed on the entire British public during
the war years and the sense of shared struggle
galvanised the nation and won George and Elizabeth
the admiration of the British people even as the
Blitz dragged on for eight long months through to
May 1941. By the time it ended over 40,000 British
civilians were killed and two million homes
had been damaged or destroyed, the majority
of the damage being inflicted on London.
The worst of the Blitz and the naval blockade
ended in the spring of 1941. This was entirely
owing to the general drift of the conflict.
Between the summer of 1940 after the swift fall
of France, Britain and the North Atlantic became
the crucible of the war. The king needed to be
visible during this, Britain’s darkest hour in
the conflict. However, from the summer of 1941
onwards the focus of matters shifted as Hitler
and the Nazis abandoned their designs on
forcing Britain to surrender and instead
turned their attentions eastwards to the Soviet
Union, undertaking the largest land invasion
in military history. Thereafter the Eastern
Front became the focus of the war in Europe,
while after the entry of the United States
into the conflict in December 1941 Britain,
the US and the Commonwealth nations turned their
attentions to gaining victory in the North Africa
campaign against the Italians and the German
expeditionary force which had been dispatched
there. They finally emerged victorious in the
spring of 1943, after which a Southern Front was
opened in Italy by the Western Allies. Twelve
months later, in the summer of 1944, a Western
Front was established with the D-Day landings and
the invasion of France. From that point onwards,
the course of the war and the result seemed
destined to be one of Allied victory.
In September 1940, in the aftermath of the
evacuation of the British Expeditionary Force
from Dunkirk in northern France earlier that
summer, and the commencement of the Blitz and
the Battle of the North Atlantic, George
championed the creation of two new awards
which would be bestowed by the crown. The George
Cross and the George Medal were both created in
September 1940. Unlike the Victoria Cross, which
had been established during the long reign of
George’s great-grandmother, and other military
honours, the George Cross and George Medal were
to be awarded to anyone who was deemed to have
conducted themselves with gallantry and bravery,
be they civilians or soldiers. In the context
of the Blitz, when ordinary Londoners,
and in particular fire-fighters and police, were
effectively the front line soldiers in the war
against Germany, such awards were deemed necessary
by the king. The George Cross would become the
civilian equivalent of the Victoria Cross, the
highest military award of its kind. In announcing
the creation of the new honour, the king stated
that, quote, “I have decided to create, at once,
a new mark of honour for men and women in all
walks of civilian life. I propose to give my
name to this new distinction, which will consist
of the George Cross, which will rank next to the
Victoria Cross, and the George Medal for wider
distribution.” It was to be awarded for “acts of
the greatest heroism or of the most conspicuous
courage in circumstances of extreme danger.”
Over the course of the war George would
personally present the awards to dozens
of soldiers and civilians. Those who were
honoured included the likes of Stuart Archer,
a bomb-diffusing expert who had diffused over 200
bombs that had landed undetonated in England by
September 1941. John Bridge was another medal of
the Cross for his role in defusing dozens of bombs
which landed in urban centres across England.
The George Medal was granted in similar cases,
often to members of the Commonwealth nations. For
instance, Margaret Irene Anderson, an Australian
staff nurse on board the Empire Star, was awarded
the Medal for her gallantry during the evacuation
of Singapore in the face of the Japanese onslaught
in 1942. Back home, Charity Bick was awarded the
George Medal by the king. She had lied about her
age at just 14 in order to be accepted into the
Air Raid Precautions unit in 1939. During an
air raid on West Bromwich by the Germans the
following August she delivered messages on her
bicycle to a nearby RAF control room and helped
her father put out an incendiary bomb that fell
on the roof of a shop. In awarding these honours
to individuals like Archer, Bridge, Anderson
and Bick, George galvanised public sentiment to
continue the struggle against Germany during the
dark days of late 1940 and early 1941 when Britain
stood largely alone against the Nazi threat.
George and Elizabeth contributed to the war cause
in other ways. From 1940 onwards the king and the
queen consort were regular visitors to hospitals
and various fronts in England and further afield.
From the summer of 1940 onwards they regularly
visited sites of extensive bombing raids to
console the victims’ relatives and to meet
the wounded. Often these duties were divided
up, with George heading for military bases and
Elizabeth touring London’s hospitals and those in
the other major cities. One might look at these as
merely symbolic gestures, but symbolic gestures
at a time of civilian endurance were what was
needed at the time and the king and queen earned
plaudits for their very visible public presence
throughout the Blitz and the remainder of the
war. As the focus of the conflict shifted away
from Britain in 1941 and the Western Allies
began taking the offensive on several fronts,
George often left England, heading to the
front lines in North Africa and the island
fortress of Malta in 1943 and visiting France,
the Low Countries and Italy in 1944 after the
Southern and Western Fronts had been opened.
By 1944 the war was entering its final stages as
Germany found itself being advanced on from
the east by the Soviets and from the south
and west by the Western Allies. George did not
play an entirely silent role in these affairs.
He made some contributions towards Allied
strategy, notably in 1943 when he proposed
that the Allies should forego opening a new front
in France in favour of pushing resources into the
Southern Front in Italy, a strategy which
Churchill was considerably in favour of and
sent along to the military chiefs of staff.
In the end, though, George saw the logic of
opening a front in northern France and on the
evening of the D-Day landings he delivered a
rousing broadcast in which he recalled the grim
position Britain had been in four years earlier,
before stating that, quote, “once more a supreme
test has to be faced. This time, the challenge is
not to fight to survive but to fight to win the
final victory for the good cause.” That eventual
victory would take another eleven months to
secure, but in the end as Soviet troops closed on
central Berlin and British, American, Canadian and
other Allied soldiers fanned out across Germany,
Hitler killed himself and the Nazis surrendered
on the 8th of May 1945. That VE or Victory in
Europe Day, George and the rest of the royal
family appeared on the balconies of Buckingham
Palace to celebrate with the British public the
end of the near six year long struggle.
With victory in the war George’s role shifted from
being Britain’s war leader to overseeing the rapid
dismantling of its empire. Promises had been
made during the war to many interested parties
concerning increased autonomy as the reward for
helping Britain in its struggle against Nazi
Germany and the Empire of Japan. In particular,
the Cripps Mission of 1942 to India had promised
the Indian National Congress leaders such as
Mahatma Gandhi that India would be allowed to
hold elections and have greater self-determination
in the aftermath of the conflict if it committed
fully to aiding Britain in its hour of need. Now
the debt fell due. In 1947 India was granted its
independence and the British Raj was divided
up, so that the Muslim-majority areas in the
north-west and north-east became the new state of
Pakistan, though the province of East Bengal would
later become the independent nation of Bangladesh.
George briefly remained as Emperor of India even
after independence, but the title was abolished
entirely in 1948, though India and Pakistan would
remain as members of the British Commonwealth.
Thus, in the second half of the 1940s, George
was overseeing the first steps of the post-war
transition from the Empire to Commonwealth,
including the 1949 London Declaration which
was pursuant from India’s declaration of
itself as a republic and the removal of George
as head of state of that Commonwealth nation.
George was cautiously in favour of this move,
provided India remained a Commonwealth nation,
though the episode did see the Republic of
Ireland leave the Commonwealth entirely.
The further dismantling of Britain’s empire would
gather pace in the 1950s, particularly from 1957
onwards when the first wave of decolonisation
spread across Africa. By the mid-1960s Britain
would relinquish much of its control of its
territories in regions like Kenya, Uganda,
Nigeria and Rhodesia, many of which new nations
in turn became members of the Commonwealth. But
George would not live to see this. His health was
deteriorating already in the late 1940s, though he
was only just after entering his fifties. Like his
father before him, his lifelong chain smoking had
taken its toll on his health, as had the stresses
of the war years. Moreover, by the late 1940s he
was suffering from several circulatory problems
including Buerger’s Disease, which leads to
clotting of small and medium arteries and which
is also exacerbated by smoking. By 1949 matters
were serious and a planned tour of some of the
Commonwealth nations had to be cancelled, while
for a time it was feared that George would have
to have one of his legs amputated. Unsurprisingly,
by this time his eldest daughter and the heir
presumptive to the throne, Elizabeth, who was
only 23 years of age, was carrying out more and
more royal duties by the end of the decade.
Matters did not improve into the 1950s. In 1951
George had to have his left lung surgically
removed after he developed lung cancer. He was
limited in his physical movements from that point
onwards, although the king attempted to remain
active, insisting on accompanying his daughter
and her husband, Prince Philip, to London Airport
on the 31st of January 1952 when they left for a
tour of much of the empire. It was the last time
he would see his daughter and heir. George died
in his sleep a week later on the 6th of February
1952 from a coronary thrombosis at Sandringham
where he was born. He was just 56 years of age.
Owing to his premature death, Elizabeth succeeded
to the throne of Britain at just 25 years of age
and as she lived to be 96 years herself her reign
would be the longest in British history. News of
George’s death was released immediately and the
mechanisms for the holding of a state funeral
were put in place. His body lay in state at
Westminster from the 11th of February onwards so
that the British public could pay their respects
to the wartime king. His funeral was held on the
15th like those of so many British monarchs at St
George’s Chapel at Windsor Castle. Afterwards
his remains were interred in the royal vault,
though they only remained here until 1969, at
which time George was reinterred in the George VI
Memorial Chapel. His remains lie there today with
those of his wife, Elizabeth, the Queen Mother,
who lived until 2002, outliving her husband
by half a century, and those of his daughter,
the recently deceased Queen Elizabeth II and her
husband the Duke of Edinburgh, Prince Philip.
George VI led Britain through one of the
most consequential periods in world history
and arguably the most significant in Britain’s
long imperial story. For much of 1940 and 1941
the country was the only major power standing
against Nazi Germany and the fascist threat. In
that dark moment the country needed leadership.
It is generally understood to have come from
Winston Churchill, but there was also George
and Elizabeth as his queen consort who acted
as figureheads in the struggle against the Blitz
and the blockade of Britain by Germany. He rose
extremely well to that occasion. Moreover, it came
from a man who was never supposed to become king,
his older brother’s love life and to a certain
extent his difficult personality having combined
to ensure that his reign was a short one and
Edward had to abdicate in favour of George in
December 1936. When he did become King of Britain,
George cannot be said to have been a philosopher
king or a particularly forceful personality, but
he offered a steady hand and humility at the helm
of state which was fitting for the time period
in which he became monarch. Overcoming his own
personal limitations, he won the respect
of the British people throughout the war,
developed a close relationship with Churchill and
managed the transition from empire to commonwealth
well in the aftermath of the conflict. Tragically,
his physical decline ensured that his reign was
cut short and that his last years were spent in
considerable pain. He should be remembered as a
modest and humble, but effective king.
What do you think of King George VI? Was it
a good thing that he became King of England and
that Edward abdicated the throne in 1936? Please
let us know in the comment section, and in the
meantime, thank you very much for watching.
George VI and Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon were born less
than five years apart. He came into the world in
December 1895. She was born on the 4th of August
1900. However, despite being born relatively
close to one another, they died half a century
apart. George’s chronic respiratory problems and
subsequent cancer led to his premature death in
February 1952 at 56 years of age. Elizabeth would
live for a little over 50 years longer, dying in
March 2002 at 101 years of age. In that time, she
became known as the Queen Mother, the matriarch
of the royal family who lived to see her children,
grandchildren and many of her great-grandchildren
grow up. There is no sign that she ever
contemplated remarrying or another relationship.
Instead, she continued the work she had carried
out while Bertie was alive. She remained a rock
of stability and offered advice to her daughter,
the new monarch, Queen Elizabeth II, where
previously she had been the pillar that her
husband relied on in the dark days of the war. No
other royal would epitomise the modernisation of
the monarchy as much as the Queen Mother did. When
she was born, Queen Victoria sat on the throne
and Britain’s empire stretched around the world.
When she died, the third millennium had started,
Britain’s empire was long gone and the monarchy
as an institution had been transformed.
The woman known to history as ‘Queen Elizabeth,
the Queen Mother’ was born the Honourable
Elizabeth Angela Marguerite Bowes-Lyon on the
4th of August 1900 at St Paul’s Walden Bury,
a modest stately home near Hitchen
in Hertfordshire, England.
One of ten children altogether, Elizabeth was the
fourth and youngest daughter of Claude Bowes-Lyon,
the Lord Glamis who became the 14th Earl of
Strathmore and Kinghorne. When her father
inherited the Scottish Earldom in 1904, she became
Lady Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon. The Bowes-Lyon family
is descended from the Royal House of Scotland,
with one of Elizabeth’s 14th-century ancestors
becoming the Thane of Glamis, whose family
seat was Glamis Castle the setting of William
Shakespeare’s Macbeth some 300 years earlier.
Her mother was Lady Cecilia Cavendish-Bentinck,
a descendent of William Cavendish-Bentinck,
the 3rd Duke of Portland and a former Prime
Minister of Great Britain from 1783, and then
of the United Kingdom between 1807 and 1809.
Spending most of her childhood between
Glamis Castle and St Paul’s Walden Bury,
she engaged in field sports and enjoyed the
company of dogs and horses. Of all her siblings
she was particularly close to her young brother
David. There was only a two-year age difference
between them, and they were often inseparable
and liked to play pranks on people together.
Elizabeth was also extremely well educated due
to her private tutoring at home, and by the age
of 10, spoke French fluently. For a time she
was educated by a German Jewish governess Käthe
Kübler and passed the Oxford Local Examination
with distinction at the age of thirteen.
The Great Britain in which Elizabeth grew up
would have appeared to her peaceful and tranquil,
and Elizabeth’s status as a Lady and as a
member of the upper classes meant that she had
a relatively easy life. Through the Victorian era,
Great Britain had become one of the most advanced
countries in the world thanks to its pre-eminence
in trade and an empire that reached all four
corners of the globe. However, it was not without
momentous social and political change.
Between 1910 and 1914, ‘The Great Unrest’ as
it was termed, saw a mass upsurge in labour
militancy and wave upon wave of strikes. Four
thousand strikes were recorded involving around
four million workers over that period and trade
union membership rose from 2 million to just over
4 million. Some actions were aggressive, violent
and insurgent. This was seen during the bitter
South Wales coal strike in Tonypandy in 1910;
the railway and dock strikes of 1911; and in a
general strike of transport workers in Liverpool
in the same year which resulted in clashes between
strikers and troops. Triggered by anger over poor
wages, a 70-hour week and compulsory overtime,
mass picketing at Llanelli railway station, on
the critical route from London to Ireland via
the ferry at Fishguard, was brutally suppressed by
the police and troops. Two men were shot dead and
many others were wounded. The troops’ action led
to a day of widespread disorder and rioting.
A movement to gain
women’s right to vote eventually succeeded through
acts of parliament in 1918 and 1928. It had become
a national movement during the Victorian era with
the formation of the National Society for Women’s
Suffrage founded in 1872. It remained largely
ineffective even after the creation of the more
vocal National Union of Women’s Suffrage Societies
led by Millicent Fawcett which still maintained
it could achieve its aims through peaceful means.
The campaign took on a more militant face with the
establishment of the Women’s Social and Political
Union, led by Emmeline Pankhurst and her daughters
Christabel and Sylvia. These were the suffragettes
whose tactics included parades, hunger strikes,
stone throwing, and smashing windows. In 1913,
Suffragette Emily Davison became a martyr to the
cause by throwing herself under the King’s horse
at the Epsom Derby that year. While politics was
put on hold at the start of the First World War,
limited suffrage was however extended in 1918
not only to 8.4 million women but also to
5.6 million disenfranchised men. 1928 saw
legislation to extend suffrage to all men
and women over the age of 21.
Another crucial moment which would come to
dominate British history and the life of
Elzabeth Bowes-Lyon in the 20th century
was the political situation in Ireland.
A movement aimed at gaining self-government for
the island of Ireland had become the dominant
movement in Irish nationalism since the 1870s.
Successive Home Rule Bills championed by the
Liberals had been defeated towards the end
of the 19th century either in the House of
Commons or the House of Lords. A third attempt in
1912 was seen as only effecting moderate reforms
and inflamed militant nationalists eventually
leading to the Easter Rising in 1916, the Irish
War of Independence and a treaty creating the
Irish Free State with Dominion status in 1922,
which allowed for the six-counties of the
north to remain part of the United Kingdom.
The Irish Republic came into being in 1937.
While these three issues dominated Elizabeth’s
early years, they would eventually be eclipsed by
the outbreak of the First World War on the 4th of
August 1914, her 14th birthday. During the war,
her home of Glamis Castle became a convalescent
hospital for troops who had been injured in the
conflict, but who were expected to make a full
recovery, and so did not need as much medical
attention as other patients. Elizabeth was
too young to become a nurse, but she did assist
with welfare work, tending to wounded soldiers,
and helping with their rehabilitation, and by all
accounts was very popular and well-liked. Four of
her older brothers served during the First World
War. Her brother Fergus was an officer in the
Scottish Black Watch Regiment but was wounded and
killed in action during the 1915 Battle of Loos.
Her brother Michael was also a soldier, and on the
28th of April 1917 was reported missing in action.
It was later discovered that he had been wounded,
taken captive, and moved to a prisoner-of-war
camp, where he stayed until the end of the
conflict. Strangely, one of the soldiers Elizabeth
cared for, wrote in her autograph book that
she was to be ‘Hung, Drawn and Quartered … Hung
in diamonds, drawn in a coach and four, and
quartered in the best house in the land.’
By tradition, young women from noble and
gentry families would be presented at court at the
start of the social season. After being presented
to the British sovereign, these debutants, as
they were called, were allowed to take part in
all manner of balls, parties, and horse-racing
events which was a sign that they were eligible
for marriage. Elizabeth was presented to
King George V in 1919. She was, however,
no stranger to the royal family with the children
of the then King George and Queen Mary occasional
visitors at her home at Glamis Castle in Scotland.
In 1922, she acted as one of the bridesmaids at
the wedding of their only daughter, Princess Mary
to the 6th Earl of Harewood, Henry Lascelles.
During one such high society event, Elizabeth was
introduced to Princess Mary’s brother, Albert,
known as ‘Bertie’ within the family and who at
that time was second in line to the throne. Albert
first proposed to her in 1921 when she was just
twenty years old, but Elizabeth turned him down,
fearing the restrictions that a royal marriage
might bring to her life. Elizabeth did eventually
accept his proposal and on the 13th of January
1923, their engagement was publicly announced.
Albert's choice of Elizabeth was seen
at the time as the monarchy modernising,
as previously it was common for princes to
marry members of other royal houses.
Prince Albert and Lady Elizabeth were wed on the
26th of April 1923 in Westminster Abbey, the first
Royal Wedding to be held there since that of Anne
of Bohemia to Richard II in 1382. Breaking with
tradition, Elizabeth placed her wedding flowers on
top of the Tomb of the Unknown Warrior to honour
her brother Fergus. Lady Elizabeth henceforth
became Her Royal Highness the Duchess of York.
After their wedding, she and Prince Albert quickly
began to perform royal engagements together. Their
first joint appearance after their wedding was
at the RAF procession in Hendon held on the 30th
of June 1923. One of the most significant royal
engagements they had together however was in July
2024, when they visited Northern Ireland. Due
to the success of this visit, the then Labour
government decided that the couple should embark
on a tour of East Africa from December 1924 to
April 1925. However, in November 1924, the
Conservatives defeated Labour in the general
election, against a backdrop of political unrest
in what was then known as Anglo-Egyptian Sudan,
modern Sudan and South Sudan, which saw the
assassination of the Governor-General Sir Lee
Stack. Despite this, Albert and Elizabeth decided
to embark on their royal tour, visiting Aden,
Uganda, Anglo-Egyptian Sudan, and Kenya, though
they avoided Egypt due to political tensions.
Around this time Elizabeth encouraged her husband
to see a speech therapist. All his life Albert
had dreaded making speeches because of a severe
stammer. His closing speech at the British Empire
Exhibition in 1925 had proved a particular ordeal.
The couple were introduced to an Australian speech
therapist called Lionel Logue who suggested daily
hour-long vocal exercises which greatly reduced
his stammer and gave him greater confidence
in public speaking. Whenever Albert was due
to make a speech, Logue was often called in, and
he was regularly invited to the royal family's
Christmas dinner to oversee the King’s Christmas
message. The relationship was later dramatized in
the 2010 film The King’s Speech, directed by Tom
Hooper and which starred Geoffrey Rush as Logue,
Colin Firth as King George VI and Helena
Bonham Carter in the role of Elizabeth.
On the 21st of April 1926,
their first child, Princess Elizabeth Alexandra
Mary, later to become Queen Elizabeth II,
was born. Shortly after their daughter's birth,
Albert and Elizabeth embarked on another royal
tour leaving their newborn daughter behind.
It’s known that Elizabeth greatly struggled
with leaving their daughter behind, but their
tour to Australia. Jamaca, Fiji, and back via
the Panama Canal was regarded at home as a great
success for public relations. Four years later,
their second daughter, Princess Margaret Rose, was
born on the 21st of August 1930. Margaret was born
in Glamis Castle and was the first royal baby to
be born in Scotland since 1600. The registration
of her birth was delayed, to avoid Margaret
being the 13th name in the parish register,
which was seen as a bad luck omen.
On the 20th of January 1936, King George V,
passed away from chronic bronchitis, and his
popular eldest son, Edward, the Prince of Wales,
succeeded to the throne to became King Edward
VIII, starting a brief reign that would be marred
with controversy and disapproval towards his love
life, a situation which would haunt Elizabeth’s
life forever. As Prince of Wales, Edward had
started a friendship with an American divorcee,
Wallis Simpson. He was known to be deeply in
love with her. While the relationship was widely
reported in the United States and in European
newspapers, it was largely kept out of the
British press by arm-twisting by the government
of the day. The Prime Minister Stanley Baldwin
had attempted to persuade the King to give up
the relationship and explored the possibility
of a Morganatic marriage whereby Wallis would not
become queen, and any children would not accede.
This was ultimately rejected by Baldwin and the
prime ministers of Australia, South Africa, and
Canada. Ultimately Edward VIII chose to abdicate,
addressing the nation by radio to say that he had
found it ‘impossible to carry the heavy burden of
responsibility and to discharge my duties as King,
as I would wish to do, without the help and
support of the woman I love.’ On the 10th of
December 1936, in front of Albert and their two
other brothers, Edward signed the Instrument of
Abdication. Thereafter he flew to the continent
where he eventually married Wallis Simpson.
On the 11th of December 1936, the man who was
never meant to be king, Prince Albert became
King George VI, and Elizabeth became Queen
Consort. Their coronation took place on the
12th of May 1937, the same day that Edward
was due to have been crowned. Elizabeth was
now Queen of the United Kingdom and the British
Dominions, as well as the Empress of India. The
scandal regarding Edward VIII was far from over
however. While Elizabeth was still supportive of
her husband’s decision to allow Edward to
create his elder brother Duke of Windsor,
and to retain the title of Royal Highness, on
the advice of the cabinet Wallis was not to be
given this title, a decision which was said to
have saddened the new King. However there was no
love lost between Elizabeth and Wallis. Wallis
reportedly referred to Elizabeth as ‘Cookie’,
believing that she was similar in appearance to
a fat Scottish cook, and Elizabeth was known to
simply call Wallis ‘that woman’. Elizabeth
remained bitter that the abdication had
forced her husband onto the throne reluctantly and
unprepared. She also remained convinced that these
events had ultimately shortened her husband’s
life, leaving her a relatively young widow.
In the Spring of 1938,
the political climate across Europe was tense, and
talk of war was common. A royal tour of France was
organised to cement relations between Britain and
France in the face of potential German aggression.
Five days before the royal couple’s departure the
Queen’s mother, the Countess of Strathmore died.
The trip to France was postponed and the court
went into three week’s mourning and dressed in
black, to be replaced after a few weeks by grey
and then mauve after that. The queen’s couturier,
Norman Hartnell, had already devised a wardrobe
for the trip to France in pastel colours and
floral patterns which was now regarded as
entirely inappropriate. Thinking on his
feet he came up with what’s become known as the
White Wardrobe, white having been the colour of
deepest mourning among medieval queens. French
queens had traditionally worn white in mourning,
and the King’s great-grandmother Queen
Victoria had been buried in white.
The team had two weeks to prepare the costumes
which were favourably received in France and
turned the Queen into an unlikely style-icon.
In March 1938, the German Chancellor Adolf Hitler
annexed neighbouring Austria in a process
known as ‘The Anschluss.’ He then turned his
attention to Czechoslovakia where around three
million people in the Sudetenland region spoke
German. Neither Britain nor France felt ready
to defend Czechoslovakia against the Germans
and were anxious to avoid military intervention
at any cost. Both countries believed that peace
could only be maintained by making territorial
concessions. The British Prime Minister Neville
Chamberlain proposed a four-power conference
in Munich to discuss the situation at which
Hitler promised to find peaceful means to resolve
differences within Europe. Chamberlain returned to
London pledging ‘peace in our time.’ The Royal
Family and the Prime Minister had always had a
close relationship, and after the signing of the
Munich Agreement on the 30th of September 1938,
Neville Chamberlain joined the King and
Elizabeth on the balcony of Buckingham Palace,
the first Prime minister to ever do this,
and received rapturous cheers from the crowd.
This sense of unity and patriotism was to be
short-lived. Chamberlain and the actions he
took against Hitler may have been popular
with the public, but politically this was
regarded as a different matter. Elizabeth
had been wholly supportive of Chamberlain
and had agreed that Hitler must be dealt with
delicately, but the House of Commons were highly
critical of Chamberlain’s solution.
Following the 1938 Munich Agreement,
both Britain and France quickly moved to rearm
with many believing that war with Germany was now
inevitable. From May to June that year King George
and Elizabeth embarked on a tour of Canada and the
United States. This was the first-time reigning
monarchs had embarked on a tour of the country.
During the trip, a veteran from the Boer War
asked Elizabeth whether she considered herself
Scottish or English, to which she replied
that she was a Canadian. This response and
the tour in general were extremely successful and
changed the public perception of King George and
Elizabeth many of whom had believed the couple to
be less suitable to royal life than Edward VIII.
Speaking to the then Canadian prime minister,
William Lyon Mackenzie King, Elizabeth expressed
her belief that the Canadian tour was the making
of George and Elizabeth as King and Queen, and
that she would continue to return to Canada often
throughout the rest of her life, whether that be a
visit for work or pleasure.
This trans-Atlantic tour was seen not only as
an opportunity to assert British dominion over
Canada, but also as a means of ensuring American
support and involvement in the event of war in
Europe. While in the United States the royal
couple spent some time with President Franklin
D. Roosevelt, and the First Lady, Eleanor
Roosevelt, even staying with them at the
White House and their residence in the Hudson
Valley. The American First Lady reportedly
spoke highly of Elizabeth and considered her
a suitable and capable monarch and Queen.
By the early part of 1939 Hitler had become
determined to invade Poland. In a cat’s-cradle
of alliances, Britain and France had pledged
to support Poland if it should be attacked
by Germany. Meanwhile, in secret negotiations,
Hitler signed a non-aggression pact with Russia,
agreeing to share Poland after the invasion. The
scene was set for war. Germany invaded Poland on
the 31st of August 1939 prompted by a false
flag attack and a day later Britain declared
war on Germany. A massive evacuation plan was
ordered to take civilians, mainly children, away
from the cities and ports in an operation called
Pied Piper. Public air raid shelters were built,
with millions of so-called Anderson Shelters set
up in people’s gardens. After the surrender of
France in June 1940, England remained as Germany’s
sole enemy, and Hitler planned to undertake an
amphibious invasion ordering the Luftwaffe to
establish complete dominance in the skies over
England in preparation. War came to London in
earnest on the 7th of September when hundreds
of German bombers and fighter planes descended
on London in what became known as the Blitz.
The operation lasted for 57 nights in a row.
The targets for the bombers were principally
in the East End of London and the docks. But very
few parts of the capital escaped, with Buckingham
Palace bombed on at least nine occasions.
The King and Queen refused to leave the
country during the blitz despite the inherent
dangers and as obvious targets for enemy action.
Elizabeth insisted also that her daughters should
remain too, against the advice that they should
be sent to Canada. In a letter to Queen Mary,
Elizabeth described one bomb attack on the Palace
which saw a direct hit in the quadrangle, and
the destruction of the palace chapel. She spoke
of her pride in the behaviour of the servants.
Just a short time later, in an act which was to
enamour the King and Queen to the British people,
she visited a bomb site in West Ham where she
spoke of ‘walking in a dead city, all the houses
evacuated, and yet through the broken windows,
one saw all the poor little possessions,
photographs, beds, just as they were left.’
During the Blitz, the Royal couple were seen
as key in keeping up morale and helping the war
effort. They came to be seen as the embodiment
of the struggle against fascism and as a
reminder of what the British were fighting for.
Rejecting the advice to flee to safety abroad,
Elizabeth was quoted as saying, ‘The children
will not leave unless I do. I shall not leave
unless their father does, and the King will not
leave the country in any circumstances.’
Queen Elizabeth contributed to the war effort
in many other ways. For example, she sponsored
the publication of The Queen’s Book of the Red
Cross. Appearing in November 1939, this book aimed
to help the funding for the Red Cross during the
war. Its authors included A.A. Milne, who wrote
the Winnie the Pooh stories, the novelist Daphne
du Maurier, and the poet T.S. Eliot, and included
photography by a close friend of the royal family,
Cecil Beaton, along with artwork by Arthur
Wragg. Using her position and role as a caring
and doting mother, Elizabeth would also take part
in radio broadcasts and try to comfort and help
encourage families that had been separated
during the war, whether it was children who
had been evacuated to the countryside, or
fathers who were fighting overseas.
Many members of the staff working at
Buckingham Palace were fighting in the army,
so Elizabeth and her husband would spend their
days at Buckingham Palace, but then leave for
Windsor Castle later in the day. This was both
for their own personal safety and to be closer
to their family. Elizabeth was always known
for being an extremely hard-working royal,
and this was evident even during the Second World
War. Elizabeth would visit troops, factories,
hospitals, and any other places that were
targeted by the German Luftwaffe. She also paid
numerous visits to the East End of London. Despite
Elizabeth’s best intentions, these planned visits
did not always go down well with the crowd.
Elizabeth was sometimes met with hostility,
especially regarding her fashion choices in
a time of war. The people of the East End
found Elizabeth’s choice of brightly coloured and
clearly expensive clothes to be distasteful, and
a clear representation of the separation between
Elizabeth and them. However, Elizabeth and her
stylist, Norman Hartnell, had deliberately chosen
to not wear black, as it was felt that black was
reminiscent of funerals and could be seen as
a bleak and depressing colour. She regarded
the colours she wore as a token of hope. After
Buckingham Palace was bombed, Elizabeth stated
that she was almost relieved as she believed that
she could now be seen as an equal to those living
in the East End. Elizabeth's actions and sense
of duty during the war, and the significance
of her being a wartime queen, remains one of
the things she is fondly remembered for.
Édouard Daladier, the French wartime prime
minister, held Elizabeth in high esteem and
was impressed by her conduct as queen and the
support and encouragement she gave to her husband
and the people of her country. It’s believed that
Hitler believed the same, describing her as ‘the
most dangerous woman in Europe,’ and describing
her popularity as a threat to German interests.
And so, despite her wariness and disapproval of
the conflict, many historians regard her character
and actions as key and central to the winning
of the Second World War, as was the strong bond
that developed between her, the King and Winston
Churchill, who became Prime Minister after the
resignation of Neville Chamberlain in May 1940.
The Second World War came to an end on
the 2nd of September 1945, In the general
election that followed shortly afterwards,
there was a surprise defeat for Britain’s
wartime leader Winston Churchill, and a Labour
government was returned under Clement Atlee,
triggering a period of considerable social change,
most notably the creation of the Welfare State.
The political views of the British Royal
family, in the past century at least,
have been a closely guarded secret and whilst
it can never be fully known where Elizabeth’s
true political beliefs and alliances lay, many
historians do believe that she was one of the
most supportive Conservative monarchs.
However, it is rumoured that Elizabeth
had told her close friend, the British
politician and journalist Woodrow Wyatt,
that she liked and was fond of the Labour
Party, despite the popular historical belief
that Elizabeth thought that only the poor and
uneducated voted for Labour. Elizabeth had also
told her family member, the Duchess of Grafton,
that she actually loved the communists.
However, Elizabeth wasn’t always the
perfect royal. Whilst the King, Elizabeth,
and their children were touring South Africa in
1947, Elizabeth mistook one of their admirer's
excitement at seeing the royal family as an
act of attempted violence, and as a result,
hit him with her umbrella from the royal car.
However, this is regarded as the only incident
of Elizabeth breaking royal protocol and acting
unprofessionally. This same year, 1947, saw her
eldest daughter, Princess Elizabeth, marry Prince
Philip, a former Prince of Greece and Denmark.
Philip had been corresponding with her daughter
since she was 13 years of age in 1939, and after
serving in the Royal Navy during the war asked the
King for his daughter’s hand in marriage in 1946.
The King consented but asked for the engagement
to be delayed until Princess Elizabeth’s 21st
birthday. The ceremony took place at Westminster
Abbey on the 20th of November 1947.
Some biographers have suggested that Elizabeth and
other members of the royal family had disapproved
of Philip’s relationship with Princess Elizabeth,
partially because his sisters had married German
noblemen who had Nazi links, but also because he
was without financial means. His family had been
exiled from Greece after his uncle was forced
to abdicate for military failures during the
Greco-Turkish war in 1922. Elizabeth is believed
to have initially teased Philip by giving him the
nickname, ‘The Hun,’ though later conceded that
he was indeed an English Gentleman. Following the
wedding, The King and Queen were due to embark on
another royal tour of Australia and New Zealand
in 1948, but the trip had to be delayed due
to the King’s deteriorating health.
In their
public broadcast to the nation in April 1948,
celebrating their silver wedding anniversary,
the King thanked his consort Elizabeth and spoke
very highly of her and of her constant support
throughout their marriage. That year George VI
had to stop public appearances for a period of
time because of a pain that he felt in his right
leg and foot, one that the doctors believed to be
Thromboangiitis Obliterans, also known as Buerger
Disease. His case, where his arteries had become
severely hardened and had become swollen, was
so severe that amputation had been considered.
On the 12th of March 1949, the King endured a
procedure known as a right lumbar sympathectomy,
an injection given in his leg to relieve him of
his pain by blocking the sympathetic nerves in
the leg. While both the King and Elizabeth were
dealing with these issues surrounding his health,
they also became grandparents on the 14th of
November 1948 when Prince Charles was born to
Princess Elizabeth and Prince Philip.
Throughout the remainder of her life,
Elizabeth would share an incredibly close
bond with her grandson and was central to
encouraging him in his passion
for the arts and culture.
Even though King George VI appeared to be
recovering and seemed to be in better health,
it was Princess Elizabeth and Prince Philip who
embarked on the royal tour of Canada in place of
the King and Queen in October 1951, the Princess’s
first tour of Canada. This was a year after the
birth of their daughter, Princess Anne on the 15th
of August 1950. The King’s last public appearance
with his wife Elizabeth was in May 1951, when they
opened the Festival of Britain together in front
of an audience of 3,000 people. This festival was
aimed at restoring patriotism and pride in being
British, as well as being a celebration of the end
of rationing and victory in the Second World War.
However, just a few months later on the
23rd of September 1951, the King underwent a
pneumonectomy, the removal of his left lung at
home in Buckingham Palace after a lung cancer
diagnosis which was due to his heavy smoking.
By December the King had somewhat recovered,
although in his Christmas Day address on the
25th of December 1951, it was clear that his
speech sounded slower and his voice was deeper
than usual, although this was most likely due to
the removal of his left recurrent laryngeal nerve
during the surgery, which can affect the sound of
one’s voice.
Whilst the King was attempting to make a full
recovery in the hope of resuming his royal duties,
his daughter Princess Elizabeth and her
husband Philip embarked on another royal
tour of the Commonwealth, this time taking in
Kenya, New Zealand and Australia starting in
January 1952. Before they left for this royal
tour, Albert had decided to wave them off at
London airport before their departure, despite
medical advice not to. This was the last time
that Elizabeth would ever see her father, and
it was the King’s last ever public appearance.
The British public had been kept in the dark
about the health battle facing the King, and so
for many it was a shock to see George VI looking
so ill on the newsreels in the cinema. On the 6th
of February 1952, King George VI passed away in
his sleep. The royal physician Dr. James Ansell
declared that the King had died from a coronary
thrombosis. It was believed that Ansell had not
been aware of the King’s cancer diagnosis due to
the level of privacy surrounding the royal family.
Indeed, the actual cause of the King’s death was
never actually made public. The press reported
that the King died from a blood clot in his
heart. Princess Elizabeth was given the news of
her father’s death while she was at the Treetops
Resort in Kenya by her husband Prince Philip on
6th of February 1952. She was now Queen Elizabeth,
and her mother was to be known henceforth as Her
Majesty Queen Elizabeth, the Queen Mother, a
title by which she is best known today.
Elizabeth initially struggled with the death
of her husband and chose to retire from royal
life and duties. Not only had she lost a husband,
but also her role in public life, along with her
husband’s many royal houses – Buckingham Palace,
Sandringham in Norfolk and Balmoral in Scotland.
It was decided that she should move out
of Buckingham Palace into Clarence House,
a modest residence which it’s understood
she disliked intensely, but she also chose
to buy a house on the west coast of Scotland as a
retirement home. It was the Prime Minister Winston
Churchill who visited her that summer in Balmoral
to urge her not to retreat from public life as
Queen Victoria had done after the death of her
beloved husband Albert. Churchill was keen that
she should be on hand to support her daughter
as she navigated her new role as Queen.
Subsequently, she resumed royal duties, attending
functions and openings, and flew to the United
States to receive a cheque for the George VI
memorial fund. She became a patron to more than
300 organisations and made history by becoming
the first female chancellor of London University,
and the first female Lord Warden and
Admiral of the Cinque Ports. However,
her principal role was very much as a supportive
and encouraging influence on her daughters.
The Queen Mother remained especially close to her
daughter Margaret, and due to their special bond,
they both embarked on a royal tour of the
Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, which later
became Zimbabwe, Zambia and Malawi from the 1st of
July to the 16th of July 1953. This was the Queen
Mother’s first international visit since the state
funeral of her husband on the 14th of February
1952 at Westminster Hall. Even though this royal
tour was originally scheduled to be carried out by
Princess Elizabeth, the tour was regarded as
a great success. The visit to the Federation
of Rhodesia and Nyasaland is regarded as a key
moment in her onward career as a royal figure and
kicked off a new chapter in her royal life. During
this tour the Queen Mother placed the foundation
stone for the University College of Rhodesia and
Nyasaland, now the University of Zimbabwe. In 1957
she became the university's president and would
often attend their events when possible.
Despite her support for education in Africa, there
are persistent suggestions that the Queen Mother
held racist views, however, whether they went
beyond those prevalent in society at the time
is uncertain. Some historians and biographers of
the Queen Mother report her support for racial
segregation, apartheid, and white supremacy in
Rhodesia. She has even been accused of supporting
the empire and the British rule over African
countries which she believed were not able
to rule themselves. On the other hand, a former
equerry to the Queen Mother, Major Colin Burgess,
has denied the suggestion that the Queen Mother
ever made racial insults and slurs, although he
does report in his book, Behind Palace Doors,
that she was often ignorant of current affairs.
Furthermore, the Queen Mother never publicly
voiced offensive views, if she indeed held them,
and so it is difficult to prove the veracity
of the claims. The British historian and a
former Conservative, Sir Robert Rhodes James,
has said that the Queen Mother had told him
that she did not agree with discrimination
regarding race, and opposed apartheid.
While her daughter Queen Elizabeth II was finding
her feet, she still commanded enormous respect in
the royal household. At the start of the new
Queen’s first royal tour of the Commonwealth
as monarch from 1953 to 1954, the Queen
Mother remained in Britain and acted as
the Counsellor of State. This meant that,
as a more senior member of the royal family,
the Queen Mother carried out many of the
duties commonly done by the reigning monarch,
such as signing official documents, and carrying
on royal business in the monarch’s absence.
The Queen Mother’s fondness for Scotland
is undisputed. After being widowed in 1952,
she had brought the partially derelict Barrogill
Castle and its surrounding estate, and planned
to restore the building so it could be used as
her holiday home. From the years 1953 to 1960
much work was done on the castle, including the
plastering and supply of electricity and water,
which was the first time the castle had had
these resources. From 1955 until her death,
the Queen Mother would visit the Barrogill
Castle for three weeks in August and for almost
a fortnight in October. She was said to visit this
castle as an opportunity for escapism and peace
away from the distractions of life in London.
One such distraction was her youngest daughter
Margaret's controversial relationship with former
Battle of Britain pilot, Group Captain Peter
Townsend. Townsend had served as King George VI’s
equerry, or assistant, from 1944 until the King’s
death and had been kept on by the new queen. Peter
Townsend was also appointed as the comptroller to
the Queen Mother in 1952, which meant that he
was charged with overseeing the spending of her
royal household. According to several sources,
Princess Margaret first met Peter Townsend when
she was fourteen, but the romance only began eight
years later, after the death of her father. The
Group Captain was 16 years older than Margaret
and later confessed that he had been attracted
to her intense beauty and sense of humour. The
relationship had been kept from the public eye,
but an off-guard moment at the Queen’s
coronation where Margaret was seen to pick some
fluff of the Group Captain’s uniform, fuelled
speculation in the international press.
Townsend had served in the Indian
Civil Service and when he returned to Britain
he’d married Cecil Rosemary Pratt, Marchioness
of Camden after a short engagement and the couple
had had two sons. After his wife’s infidelity,
he filed for divorce. It was his status as a
divorcee that made it impossible for him to
marry Margaret as it was against the teachings of
the Church of England. Parliament was also firmly
against the union. As Defender of the Faith, the
head of the Church of England, her sister the
queen was unable to sanction the relationship.
A compromise was proposed. Under the terms of
the Royal Marriages Act of 1772, no descendant
of George II could marry without the permission
of the reigning monarch. It was suggested
that Margaret and Peter Townsend wait until
the princess turned 25 years of age and was thus
deemed to be capable of making her own decisions.
Townsend was posted to Brussels as an air attaché
at the British Embassy, but even by the time of
Margaret’s 25th birthday, the Queen had still
not given her approval for the marriage.
Despite changing attitudes, and a lingering
sadness among the British public that Edward
VIII had been unable to marry for love and retain
his royal status, permission was still not given.
The Prime Minister of the time, Anthony Eden, was
himself a divorcee and had subsequently remarried,
and one might expect that he would be sympathetic
to the Princess's plight. Eden did amend the Royal
Marriages Act, but in a way that was regarded as
cruel and unfair. The change would have allowed
Margaret and Townsend’s marriage, but the Princess
and their future children would be removed from
the line of succession as a result. Whilst Eden
did highlight that Margaret’s removal from the
succession would not affect her status as a royal
in any way, in the end Margaret chose not to marry
Townsend. On the 31st of October 1955, Princess
Margaret made her position clear that she was
mindful of the teachings of the church, and was
conscious of her duty to the Commonwealth, and
that she had decided to put these considerations
before any others. Margaret was said to be
heartbroken, but ultimately moved on.
Despite tension and friction between
her daughters, the Queen Mother lived a rather
peaceful private life as a widow. Her love for
field sports and animals continued throughout her
life, and now as Queen Mother she had more time to
dedicate to these passions. A deep affection for
horses was a love shared between the whole family,
as her daughter Queen Elizabeth II was also an
avid admirer, and she developed a new interest
in steeplechasing, a race in which horses must
jump over various fences and terrain obstacles.
This fascination with the sport came as a result
of her friendship with Anthony Bingham Mildmay,
the second Baron Mildmay of Flete, who was an
amateur steeplechaser. He sat next to the Queen
Mother at a dinner in Windsor Palace in 1949,
where he struck up a conversation with the then
queen, in which he recommended that Elizabeth
should buy a horse that she could share with
her daughter Princess Elizabeth. With the
help of Mildmay’s trainer, Peter Cazalet,
the horse Monaveen, was selected for the royals,
and this horse won its first race at the Fontwell
Park Racecourse in October 1949, where it won
the Chichester Handicap Race. The Queen Mother’s
horses won 500 steeplechase races, and she was
an avid follower of every steeplechase race,
even having the commentaries piped directly
to her place of residence in Clarence House,
although it is unclear whether she actually
placed bets on these races or not.
As well as a love for horses,
the Queen Mother also enjoyed angling. In 1982,
after nearly choking on a fish bone and having
to have the stuck bone removed surgically
at Aberdeen Royal Infirmary, she joked that
that incident was simply an act of revenge by
the salmon she had caught. Another lifelong
interest was collecting various artworks. Whilst
she acquired most of her large collection during
her time as reigning monarch, she was always
continually adding to her collection of art and
often developed a close bond with her favourite
artists, such as John Piper or Edward Seago.
She also had a liking for artwork that had been
inspired by previous royals, such as the sketches
made by the Scottish painter Sir David Wilkie for
his portrait of Queen Victoria in her youth. She
was also supportive of artists who had been active
in the Second World War. Among many other works,
her collection included paintings by Monet and
Augustus John and a number of Fabergé Eggs.
It was not long before the love life of
Elizabeth’s daughter Margaret took centre stage
again. In the late fifties, she embarked on an
initially scandalous affair with a photographer,
Antony Armstrong-Jones. Once again, the liaison
was kept secret from the public and yet there
are suggestions that the Queen Mother not
only knew about her daughter’s affair but
actively encouraged it. At the time Margaret
shared Windsor’s Royal lodge with her mother,
and it’s been reported by biographers that the
Queen Mother grew fond of the photographer,
whom she dubbed ‘Tony.’ Soon Margaret was
paying secret visits to Armstrong-Jones’s
studio in Pimlico, and he was a frequent visitor
to the Lodge in Windsor. He did so under cover of
‘building and aviary’ for the Queen Mother.
In 1959, the Queen Mother threw a party to
welcome Princess Alexandra home from Australia,
at which it was clear that Margaret and Antony
Armstrong-Jones had feelings for one another.
They would marry a year later in a ceremony
which was the first of its kind to be televised.
On the 6th of October 1961, Armstrong-Jones was
given the title of the Earl of Snowdon.
On the 28th of May 1960, a few weeks after
his marriage to Margaret, Armstrong Jones’s
illegitimate daughter, Polly Fry, was born.
She was subsequently brought up by a close
friend of the Snowdons, and it wasn’t until
2004 that she persuaded Lord Snowdon to have
a DNA test which confirmed their link. From
his marriage to Princess Margaret the Queen Mother
had two more grandchildren, David Armstrong-Jones,
the second Earl of Snowdon on the 3rd of November
1961, and Lady Sarah Armstrong-Jones, now Lady
Sarah Chatto on the 1st of May 1964. Nevertheless,
Margaret and Antony had a turbulent marriage,
with widespread rumours of adultery and drug use.
While it’s accepted generally that Antony was the
first to be unfaithful, Margaret went on to have
affairs of her own. The couple divorced in 1978
in what was the first royal divorce since the
annulment of Henry VIII’s marriage to Anne of
Cleeves in 1540. The Queen Mother maintained
a close relationship with Armstrong-Jones,
and it was believed that many members of the royal
family supported him after their divorce.
Increasingly the Queen Mother
encountered ill health. In February of 1964, she
underwent an emergency appendectomy, which led to
the postponement of her planned royal tour of the
Commonwealth countries of Australia, New Zealand
and Fiji for two years. After the procedure, the
Queen Mother recovered aboard the Britannia, the
royal family’s cherished yacht, during a Caribbean
cruise. She would have two battles with cancer,
with the first in December 1966 when she underwent
an operation to remove a cancerous tumour after
her colon cancer diagnosis. In 1984, the Queen
Mother was diagnosed with cancer for the second
time. She was then given a diagnosis of breast
cancer, which resulted in the removal of a lump
in her breast. The public was not made aware
of these health challenges at the time. Indeed,
these issues with her health did not stop her from
undertaking her royal duties, and she continued to
be one of the most hardworking royals for the
rest of her life. She embarked on over forty
official royal overseas visits, notably visiting
Iran in 1975 at the invitation of the country’s
last monarch, the Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi.
She was warmly received there and it was reported
that many were amused by the fact that the Queen
Mother would engage in conversation with anyone,
regardless of their hierarchy or status. Despite
her busy schedule, time was always set aside for
leisure. Between 1976 and 1984, she would visit
France to spend her summer there every year,
and she would embark on her own private trips
to other European countries up until 1992.
In 1981, the Queen Mother’s favourite
grandson Charles married Lady Diana Spencer.
Diana’s grandmother Ruth, Lady Fermoy, had been
one of the Queen Mother’s ladies-in- waiting since
1956 and Diana blamed her for turning the Queen
Mother against her. Princess Diana once told a
friend in a secretly taped conversation that her
husband’s grandmother was ‘always looking at me
with a strange look in her eyes.’ She described
it as interest and pity mixed in one. One issue
that Diana reportedly found particularly galling
was how the Queen Mother was demonstratively
preferential towards her eldest son, Prince
William over her younger son Harry. Later
documentaries would claim that the Queen Mother
would invite Prince William over for tea and not
invite Prince Harry. In later life, however,
she seems to have favoured Harry over William,
leaving him a larger share of her estate than his
elder brother. After Princess Diana’s death in a
car crash in Paris in 1997, The Queen Mother was
said to have been upset at the criticism levelled
at her daughter the Queen for being uncaring
and insensitive to the mood of the nation
In 1987,
a major controversy was revealed surrounding the
Queen Mother, one that impacted her popularity
to some degree. It was revealed that her nieces,
Nerissa Bowes-Lyon and Katherine Bowes-Lyon, had
been wrongly listed as dead by Burke’s Peerage, a
yearly publication of aristocratic genealogy and
heraldry, in 1963, claiming that Nerissa had died
in 1940 and Katherine in 1961. In 1987 the tabloid
newspaper, The Sun, published an article proving
Burke’s Peerage as wrong, and instead informing
the public the Queen Mother’s nieces were instead
living in The Royal Earlswood Hospital for people
with mental disabilities since 1941. Both were
classified as ‘imbeciles’ in the terminology of
the day. The paper revealed that neither Nerissa
nor Katherine had ever learned how to talk, and
they had essentially been cut off and ignored by
their family, other than a yearly payment of £125
to Earlswood Hospital. When Nerissa passed away in
1986, no family reportedly attended her funeral.
There have been mixed accounts regarding this
controversial chapter in the Queen Mother’s
life. A documentary produced by Channel 4
in 2011, titled The Queen’s Hidden Cousins,
included claims made by nurses who worked at the
hospital at that time that no members of the royal
family nor the Bowes-Lyon family ever visited the
girls. However, sources within the family argue
otherwise. They maintain that the two sisters were
often visited by their mother Fenella Bowes-Lyon,
the Queen Mother’s sister-in-law, until she died
in 1966. It has also been claimed that the Queen
Mother also began to develop a relationship with
her nieces after learning that they were actually
still alive in 1982, and would send them money
for presents at Christmas time and on each of
their birthdays. There has been no official
confirmation of this. Throughout her life,
the Queen Mother was heavily involved with charity
work and became patron of Mencap, supporting those
with learning disabilities in 1986.
On the 4th of August 1990, the Queen Mother
celebrated her 90th birthday. The landmark
was commemorated publicly on the 27th of
June 1990 with a parade thanking her for
her service and endurance as one of the
longest and hardest working members of the royal
family. For her 100th birthday 10 years later,
another parade was hosted to celebrate her life
and achievements. Actors such as Sir John Mills
and Sir Norman Wisdom participated, and the Royal
Bank of Scotland produced a special £20 bank note
to celebrate this momentous occasion. However,
The Queen Mother’s health was quickly failing,
although this did not prevent her from carrying
out royal duties. Despite injuring her pelvis in
December 2001, she refused to sit for
the national anthem for her husband’s
memorial service on the 6th of February 2002 as
a mark of respect for her beloved husband.
Tragedy struck for the Queen Mother on the
9th of February 2002, just three days after
the anniversary of her husband's passing,
with the death of her youngest daughter,
Princess Margaret after suffering from her fourth
stroke. Members of the royal family and the queen
herself were concerned about the Queen Mother
making the journey from her place of residence
in Norfolk to St George's Chapel in Windsor, where
Margaret was to be buried, but she flew there by
helicopter, partially so no press would be able
to take photographs of her in her wheelchair,
which she did not like to use. Her last public
appearance was on the 5th of March 2002,
when the Queen Mother attended a garden lunch
party for the Eton Beagles, a hunting society
at the prestigious Eton School.
On the 30th of March 2002, the Queen
Mother passed away with her eldest daughter at her
side at the age of 101. At the time of her death,
she was the longest living member of the British
royal family in history. Queen Elizabeth,
the Queen Mother was laid in state for three days
at Westminster Hall, and it's calculated that
200,000 people paid their respects to her there
before her funeral on the 9th of April 2002. Her
death was also marked in the Commonwealth,
with the then governor-general of Canada,
Adrienne Clarkson, asking Canadian citizens
to remember the Queen Mother and honour their
memory of her on the day of her funeral. The Queen
Mother was laid to rest beside her husband and
their daughter Margaret in St George’s Chapel,
and after her funeral, her wreath was placed on
top of the grave of the unknown soldier upon her
request, a repeat of her gesture at her wedding
some 79 years before. The Queen Mother had a major
impact on Britain throughout her life and reign,
and it was her stable and loving marriage with
King George VI and the support she provided him,
that has often been credited as saving the British
monarchy in a time of immense social and political
upheaval. Upon her death, the Queen Mother was
remembered as kind and funny, and was one of
the more liked members of the royal family, and
this has only been furthered by her depiction in
the popular Netflix drama, The Crown.
What do you think about Queen Elizabeth,
the Queen Mother? Do you think she was the
saving grace of the British monarchy? Or
were her rumoured racist views and neglect of her
nieces an insight into her true character? Please
let us know in the comment section and in the
meantime, thank you very much for watching.
George VI and the Queen Mother were an unlikely
couple to become King and Queen of the United
Kingdom. The royal succession was meant to ensure
that King Edward VIII would rule for many years,
but Edward’s determination to marry Wallis Simpson
dictated otherwise. For Britain it was probably a
serendipitous change. While Edward and Wallis
went on to court the Nazis within months of
his abdication, George began a reign that is very
well-regarded amongst Britain’s modern monarchs,
offering moral leadership during the Second World
War and carving out a successful relationship with
Winston Churchill as Britain’s wartime leader,
despite a less than promising start between the
two men. Even before he became king, Elizabeth had
been a bedrock of support for the reserved younger
son of George V, encouraging him to overcome the
speech impediment and other issues that had left
him lacking in confidence as a young man. Their
time as king and queen was notable in other ways
too. George and Elizabeth, for instance, will
forever have the distinction of being the last
Emperor and Empress of India. Together they
navigated both personal struggles and profound
political challenges, laying the groundwork
in the process for a new British monarchy that
would still have a great role to play in the world
even after the sun set on Britain’s empire.